XDeej: At the highest tier of competition, the only thing that matters are wins
Matters are wins...
and losses.
And when it comes to this measure of success there can be no
greater failure
than the Shanghai Dragons.
A team so bad. So universally representative of failure
that they hold the unbeatable record of the longest losing
streak of any professional competitive team.
While that record does outline the results, it's only a small
detail that leaves out the true value of the story.
So join me on the deep dive as we take a look at the longest
losing streak in history
And see what it finally took
To awaken the dragon
Music: [Hard Horns Punch In]
[Triumphant music continues]
[Triumphant music fades]
XDeej: Before exploring how they managed to have everything
go completely wrong
it's important to look at how they started.
When it comes to Chinese E-sports, it seems they've never
struggled to put together top-tier teams that can compete
on the world's stage.
This was also true when it came to Overwatch, as one of the
best teams in the world competing at the time
was comprised entirely of Chinese players
that were competing with, and beating, some of the best
teams in the similarly competitive Korean market
So when Miraculous Youngsters was disbanded mere months
before the Overwatch league was set to begin, there was little
doubt that many of the players on this incredible roster were
gonna end up signed to the recently announced team
of the Shanghai Dragons.
And on October 31st, the Dragons released their official
roster and...
It wasn't exactly what people were expecting.
It included Xushu from team twelve forty six,
Free Feel and Roshan from F T D gaming,
FiveKing from I G Ice, and Diya from Vici gaming.
But most curiously, Altering, MG, and Undead
All from the struggling LGD gaming team that would
end up raising some eyebrows.
MonteCristo: Could they have made a better roster perhaps,
because that's been a lot of the controversy
I think you could definitely apologize for the lead up
How you chose your players might be a good example of that
They don't have the right support players,
They have limitations in terms of their DPS,
and they may not have the right players, to actually
[Vocals Fade]
XDeej: It seems the controversy stirring before the first season
had even started was more to do with how the roster came
together rather than the players themselves.
It turns out that one of the prominent voices in its assembly was
the Shanghai Dragons head coach Chen "U4" Congshen
And where was U4 coaching before getting called up to the
majors for overwatch league...?
None other than the struggling LGD gaming team that a handful
of the players on the roster had been pulled from.
When coupled with some of the conduct concerns regarding
his... coaching style that we'll get into a little later,
It seems like that instead of assembling the best team possible,
U4 may have opted to bring in at least a small handful of players
he knew he could already push around a bit.
How he *got* the job is impossible to say based on the
extremely middle of the road performance
at his last coaching job,
But as unfortunate to the start of the situation would be
it wouldn't stave off the oncoming start of Overwatch League's
first ever season.
So, with little other choice than to soldier on and make their best
effort, the Shanghai Dragons lined up for their preseason debut
and...
the issues they would struggle with all season began to emerge
Commentator 1: In terms of the Shanghai Dragons, we're seeing not very good execution with any of their comps.
Commentator 2: And Shanghai stalled out a little bit here.
Commentator 3: Alright, so, Shanghai Dragons, clearly they need to fix the fundamentals
Commentator 2: Oh man, that is a problem for Shanghai.
Commentator 2: Shanghai just left the payload alone!
Commentator 4: Shanghai Dragons... Lacked a bit of cohesion
Commentator 4: It's not working right now for the Shanghai Dragons...
Commentator 2: This is just devastating for Shanghai
[Ticking music fades out]
[soft piano music begins]
XDeej: In the 10 games that represent the
first stage of season 1
the Shanghai Dragons would finish with a record of zero wins
and ten straight losses
Fans remained hopeful...
but when it came to their opponents, and even the
commentators of the Overwatch League,
There was little faith left that the team as it existed
would have a chance at recovery.
MonteCristo: The Shanghai Dragons seem condemned to an
eternal torture, where victory is perpetually just a *little*
bit out of reach.
The signing window has now opened.
You can end your torture.
The time is now to make these changes,
I'm looking forward to the announcements, they cannot
possibley come soon enough.
XDeej: Shanghai would eventually make the change
but far later than they probably should've.
Not only did they remain without a win for the first 8 matches of
stage 2, but they also had a losing streak of 24 straight maps
without even taking a single round of an opponent.
Desperate for a change, the Dragons added some much needed
depth to their roster.
Bringing in Ado in on DPS,
Fearless on tank, and shortly thereafter,
one more addition on off tank that would soon become
the face of the franchise.
[cymbal vibration fades out]
With the team unable to claim their first win in stage 2,
hopes were high going into stage 3 that the new additions
would be enough to tip the scales in their favor
for the team's first win in franchise history.
Unfortunately, fate would prove unkind to the Dragons once
more as the stability of the team was thrown into chaos.
[Shambali music plays]
The Dragons would lose their head coach
towards the end of stage 2
Then, they would also lose Undead, due to a litany of
scandalous allegations that would see him let go
for reasons they did not clarify.
The Dragons were without consistency in their leadership
and had to adapt to half of their roster being new.
To make matters worse, half the team now also spoke
a different language, creating numerous instances of games
being lost on a small small handful of plays where
communication issues caused catastrophic results.
Commentator: You got a lot of Chinese players speaking
Mandarin, you have a lot of Korean players who are
trying to learn English.
They're using very basic Chinese as well as some English
She wanted to ask in Chinese for healing
However she ever so slightly mispronounced something and...
She kinda just ended up swearing like a sailor
XDeej: If these issues weren't bad enough on their own,
the faceless internet mob does what it always does
and discovered that several players on the team were spending
numerous hours playing PubG
Suggesting that instead of practicing they were simply writing
off the season and spending their time playing
games and hanging out
An internal investigation was launched and of course
none of the allegations were true, but it did reveal that these
played games took place on their precious few days off
that they're allowed each month.
Despite the internet's notoriety for getting almost any form
of investigation wrong, it did provide the benefit of revealing
one piece of important information.
It seems that the Shanghai Dragons weren't just working hard,
Working hard is pretty much all they were allowed to do.
Custa: This team...
Custa: This team... Played the most
Practiced the most out of any team in the Overwatch League.
Cause we were all in the same practice facility,
we're in the same hallway, we can here them, right?
They were there first...
They were there first... and they left last.
There is rumors of practice regimes and their schedules
and stuff like that and I can probably attest to that, of like
They were just there all the f****** time.
But, Shanghai Dragons were just *endless* in their routine.
They would leave at like midnight,
They were expected to play like, hours and hours of ranked
They were at least playing like 14 hours a day.
I think they were playing like, 14 hours a day of Overwatch
[Vocals fade out]
By the time they had reached 36 straight losses,
Their entire season only had 4 more matches left
With a trio of challenging teams at the tail end of the schedule.
For their 37th match, many believed their best, and last chance
to finally claim their first win would be against the second-worst
team in the league in the 6 and 30 Florida Mayhem.
Despite coming out strong, they would drop the first round.
Commentator 1: And there it is! The Mayhem!
XDeej: Then, steel their nerve to take the second.
Commentator 1: It's a tie game here!
XDeej: And give reason to believe by pushing
ahead to take the third.
Commentator 1: And the Dragons inch ahead in the series.
It's 2 to 1!
XDeej: Only to then faulter, setting up a final fight to the finish.
Commentator 1: And it's a map 5!
XDeej: Taking this match to a map 5 made it the closest match
they'd had since their 8th of the season.
Commentator 1: It's scrubbed clean of Shanghai!
And the first round,
And the first round, to the Mayhem.
XDeej: Their first win was so close, they could taste it.
All they needed to do was win 2 rounds,
and the match was theirs.
Commentator 1: There gonna get there... And there it is!
Commentator 1: There gonna get there... And there it is! Ok!
Commentator 2: One point to decide it all.
XDeej: And after 36 straight losses,
in the absolute last round,
of the last match,
in what many considered to be their last
good chance of the season
Commentator 1: Beloved Dragons. Today...
Commentator 1: Beloved Dragons. Today... Is not your day.
XDeej: They fell short.
The Dragons would go on to lose their last
3 matches of the season as well.
All without taking a single round.
And would bring their season to a close
with an unfortunately perfect 0... and 40... record.
The Shanghai Dragons were unable to achieve
even a single victory in the entire
first season of the Overwatch League.
Not because they lacked heart
Or dedication
And not even because they lacked the skill...
They simply never had leadership.
They never had a battlefield general that could look at all of
their individual roles, and put the pieces together
when the game was on the line.
And as they looked ahead to the challenges they would face
in season 2, they would get it.
[Taiko drums beating]
While Shanghai was going through the worst ordeal
in the history of the League,
there was another team, on the opposite side of the globe
that was facing their own troubles.
After a respectable finish of 26 and 14,
Boston's winning record must have felt like an absolute miracle
considering the problems that cropped up
throughout their first season.
While the ridiculousness of their journey in season 1
is worthy of a video on its own,
Its fundamental message would ultimately show that as the
team was falling apart, one player loaded everyone
on his back to keep it together.
While it's fair to say that they had some talent on their team
It was no secret that Gamsu and his methodical tank play
were responsible for much of what they were able to achieve.
When it comes to what Shanghai was missing from season 1
the addition of a tank that could control space, secure kills,
and bring a level of play that earned not 1, not 2
but 3 player of the week nominations during the first season
was sure to bring a lot to the table.
Which made it all the more surprising that Boston would be
willing to trade him away, and perhaps slightly disappointing to
Gamsu that he would be traded to the winless Dragons.
Commentator: Gamsu did get 'shanghaied' by the dragons
he's here now, he's gonna be playing on this roster.
[Gamsu speaking Korean]
XDeej: And with that, the second season of the
Overwatch League began.
Along with a few strong additions to the team during the
offseason, the Dragons had a whole new swagger
coming into season 2.
And with the promise that he would make his new Shanghai
fans proud, the Dragons would rally around their new leader
to do battle with the rest of the league once more.
[Dramatic staccato violin playing]
Unfortunately for Shanghai, the hill they had to climb
for their first win would prove steep
as they dropped their first match of season 2
in a 3 to 1 loss against the Hangzhou Spark.
Concern would continue to mount as they found themselves
on the losing end of their second match, in a 4 to 0 pummeling
against the Vancouver Titans.
But their third match of the season was different.
Not only were they going up against a strong team.
It was the same team that Gamsu had led to a winning season
Only a few short months ago.
But now, in the third match of the season,
in the 43rd outting for the team without a win,
Gamsu would remind the Uprising what they had lost.
[Game Commentary fades in]
Welcome to the Overwatch League!
Say goodnight!
He goes off the side
Axiom now gonna get dropped
And the Shanghai Dragons are slaughtering Boston Uprising!
They will take ruins!
XDeej: After taking the first match with an emphatic statement,
Shanghai would prove they had the will to win,
by beating Boston in an overtime victory for the second match.
[Game Commentary fades in]
E M P dumped in by Ding
to try and turn things around, and it is gonna work a treat!
Note pops out, Eliminated!
The tick comes through
And Shanghai Dragons lead the series two zero.
XDeej: Now in the driver seat, and only one match away
from their first win ever, the path to victory
would be their toughest fight yet.
After starting the 3rd match by going even on rounds,
The contest would demand everything from *both* teams
As they would complete a full push on offense
to score a tie during overtime.
And after successfully defending against Boston's assault
during *double* overtime, Shanghai only needed to win
one fight to secure their first... victory... ever.
[Game Commentary fades in]
Kellex, gonna be eliminated!
Transcendence is out from AimGod, but it's gonna expire
They will be able to finish him off.
They can get it
Just a couple more percent to go!
Let'em have it Boston!
Hexiom, popping the Primal Rage, and it Does. Not. Matter.
If the reaction of those in attendance was all you had to go on,
It would be easy to think that this match
was for the League championship.
Or to set a new historic win streak.
Or maybe even to keep a team's playoff hopes alive...
But it wasn't...
The Shanghai Dragons had simply gotten a single win.
[Dramatic inspirational horns blare]
XDeej: It didn't matter who your favorite team was...
What jersey you were wearing at the time...
Or who you showed up to cheer for.
If you were there to see it,
You were a Shanghai Dragons fan.
[Inspiring orchestral music fades to angelic chorus]
Resiliency is an interesting concept.
The idea where you can be beaten down to the point where you
become stronger certainly sounds like an unusual notion.
But much like the saying goes,
The Shanghai Dragons proved that once you hit rock bottom,
there's nowhere to go, but up.
The Shanghai Dragons would finish stage 1 with a record of
3...
3... and 4...
They'd carry the momentum of improvement through stage 2
and then, only 5 short months after the team's first ever win,
The Shanghai Dragons would carry a 5 and 2 record into the
playoffs to be crowned the stage 3 champions.
[Horns swell to a rising crescendo]
Commentator 1: It's been a long time coming for this squad.
Commentator 2: No one could have seen this future.
Commentator 1: This was an incredible story, and it's something
that I think people are gonna remember for years to come.
If there's one thing I like more than a good underdog story,
It's those people who take the time to like and subscribe
And if you think there are any stories out there that deserve the
deep dive or are lesser known,
do be sure to let me know in the comments
And with that I believe my job here is done,
and until I see you next time...
Party on...
So in the year 2 season 2 championship....
Shanghai dominates Seoul Dynasty.
They are the new champions of Overwatch League.
They complete what the Cleveland Browns have never been
able to do, they got from not winning a game in year 1
to taking everything in year 2.